A Guide to the Papers of Louis I. Jaffé, 1907-1950
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Louis I. Jaffé 1907-1950
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
9924-i
Ca. 700 items (2 boxes).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This addition to the Jaffé collection was given to the Library by Mrs. Louis I. Jaffé on May 11, 1982.
Biographical/Historical Information
Louis Isaac Jaffé was born in Detroit, Michigan, February 22, 1888, the son of Phillip and Lotta Maria (Kahn) Jaffé. When Jaffé was twelve years old, his family moved to Durham, North Carolina, and he graduated from high school there in 1907. In 1911, he received an A.B. degree from Trinity College (now Duke University).
While a student at Trinity, Jaffé edited The Chronicle, a campus weekly, and was associate editor of The Archive, a college monthly. After graduation, he joined the staff of the Durham Sun, but left a short time later to become a reporter and assistant city editor for the Richmond Times- Dispatch.
In 1917, Jaffé was commissioned as Second Lieutenant in the Field Artillery Section, Officer's Reserve Corps of the United States Army. He was re-commissioned in the Aviation Section 1918, and again in 1919 with the Service of Supply. He was honorably discharged in France, March 29, 1919, and was commissioned as Inspector in the American National Red Cross with rank of Captain. He served on the Red Cross Commission to the Balkans from April to July, 1919, and was director of the Red Cross News Service in Paris from July to October, 1919. He was made a Chevalier of the State of Roumania, and honor bestowed in recognition of his work there with the Red Cross Commission.
After the war, Jaffé went to Norfolk to become editor of the Virginian-Pilot, a position he held from 1919 until his death in 1950. He was prominent among Virginia liberal journalists and won the Pulitzer Prize in 1929 for an editorial deploring a lynching which took place in Houston, Texas, on the eve of the Democratic National Convention.
In one of his last editorials, dated February 25, 1950, concerning the "mercy killing" of the Boothe bill for desegregation of Virginia public transportation he wrote: "The Virginia Democratic organization makes haste slowly in the field of social-political reform...It is still too uneasy about the impact of de-segregation on common carries to give the proposal anything like an official blessing. That will come later-after a longer look at this highly desirable reform, and possibly after another shove or two from the Supreme Court of the United States."
Scope and Content
This addition to the Louis I. Jaffé Papers, 1907-1950, consists of ca. 700 items (2 boxes), Jaffé's correspondence files "S" through "V." Some of the major correspondents include Alfred E. Smith, Senator Claude A. Swanson, E. Lee Trinkle, Norfolk city manager I. Walke Truxton, Robert B. Tunstall and William M. Tuck. The other correspondents are mainly national, state, and local newspaper editors and writers; Norfolk and Virginia government officials; local merchants and businessmen; educators and clergymen; and Virginia writers.
An extensive description of the contents of this collection was prepared by Mrs. Louis I. Jaffé, and can be found in the control folder.
Arrangement
The correspondence is arranged in alphabetical order. "S," "T," "U," and "V" have one or two general folders, followed by individual folders for the more prominent or prolific correspondents. Within the general folders, the material is arranged alphabetically, and chronologically therein. Within the individual folders, the material is arranged chronologically. Three oversize printed items have been separated from the correspondence and filed in an oversize folder.
Contents List
- "Sacramento" through "Small" 1920-1949, 70 items (Box 1)
- "Smith" through "Syer" 1919-1949, n.d., 80 items (Box 1)
- St. Vincent's Hospital 1949, 10 items (Box 1)
- Scarborough, Charles W. 1942, 8 items (Box 1)
- Schaefer 1941, 1948, 5 items (Box 1)
- Seashore State Par 1931, 1934, n.d., 25 items (Box 1)
- Seeman, Ernest 1920, 1925-1926, 1933, 6 items (Box 1)
- Simpson, R.W. 1920, 17 items (Box 1)
- Simpson, William Marks 1927, 1930, 1947, 17 items (Box 1)
- Slaughter, Sue R. 1944, 1950, 7 items (Box 1)
- Slover, S.L. 1925, 1933, 1936, 1943, 5 items (Box 1)
- Smith, Alfred C. 1926, 1 item (Box 1)
- Smith, Alfred E. 1927-1928, 5 items (Box 1)
- Smith, Oscar 1945, 1947-1949, 6 items (Box 1)
- Smith, William B. 1921-1946, 9 items (Box 1)
- Smith, W.R.L. 1927-1934, 15 items (Box 1)
- Southgate, T.S. 1921-1928, 9 items (Box 1)
- Southern Regional Council, Inc. 1944, 1950, 6 items (Box 1)
- Squires, W.H.T. 1934-1945, 6 items (Box 1)
- Starke, Lucien D. 1907, 1922-1931, 8 items (Box 1)
- Staton, Harry 1932, 1938, 10 items (Box 1)
- Sullivan, Mark 1921, 2 items (Box 1)
- Swanson, Senator Claude A. 1925, 1930-1931, 8 items (Box 1)
- Swem, E.G. 1922, 1926, 1928, 5 items (Box 1)
- "Tampo" through "Tyler" 1919-1949, 95 items (Box 1)
- Talbot, Minton W. 1929, 4 items (Box 1)
- Thompson, Dorothy 1939, 1 item (Box 1)
- Thompson, Frederick I. 1925, 5 items (Box 1)
- Thompson, Thomas P. 1924, 3 items (Box 1)
- Thurman, Beverly R. 1933, n.d., 5 items (Box 1)
- Trinkle, E. Lee 1921-1926, 1937, 15 items (Box 1)
- Truxtun, I. Walke 1926, 1929-1933, 41 items (Box 1)
- Tuck, William M. 1940, 1 item (Box 1)
- Tucker, Rt. Rev. Beverley D. 1924-1925, 1927, n.d., 5 items (Box 2)
- Tunstall, Robert B. 1921-1948, 70 items (Box 2)
- Tunstall, Virginia Lyne 1922, 1925-1927, n.d., 9 items (Box 2)
- Tunstall, Whit P. 1921-1948, 6 items (Box 2)
- Tyrrell, Henry G. n.d., 1 item (Box 2)
- "United" through "Utara" 1920-1949, 14 items (Box 2)
- Undset, Sigrid 1943, 1 item (Box 2)
- "Van Blarcom" through "Virginia War History Commission" 1920-1946, 32 items (Box 2)
- Victory Medal 1923, 2 items (Box 2)
- Viett, George F. 1924-1929, 12 items (Box 2)
- Virginia Quarterly Review 1927, 19 items (Box 2)
- Virginia State College 1944-1945, 1949, 10 items (Box 2)
- Virginia Union University 1937, 1941-1949, 9 items (Box 2)
- Certificate 1924
- Reprints of W. Orton Tewson's "An Attic Salt-Shaker" ca. 1926
- Poster ad for Virginia Quarterly Review 1927